Guide to the A. P. Watt & Son
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
A. P. Watt & Son,
1883-1917.
A.P. Watt (Firm)
1 linear ft. (240 items in 2 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079831
History
Founded in 1875 by Alexander Pollock Watt (1834-1914), A. P. Watt is the longest-established literary agency in the world. It is also one of the most dynamic and successful. The literary estates this agency represents include those of some of the foremost British and Irish writers of the 20th Century. Its current authors include leading novelists, biographers, historians, and specialist writers pre-eminent in their field. The agency also represents some outstanding children's authors and illustrators, and, in its film and television department, a select number of screenwriters and directors. A. P. Watt's clients include a Nobel Prize winner, four Booker Prize winners, three Orange Prize winners, several Whitbread Prize winners, and the first Children's Laureate. Its writers have achieved some outstanding No 1 bestsellers, several long-running television series, and three of Hollywood's top box office successes.
Scope and Content
Mostly testimonial letters from satisfied clients of A.P. Watt, praising his services. Many of the letters were published in promotional brochures. Two of these books, COLLECTION OF LETTERS ADDRESSED TO A.P. WATT BY VARIOUS WRITERS (London, 1893) & LETTERS ADDRESSED TO A.P. WATT (London, 1894), are included in the collection. There were other editions published in 1889, 1898, 1899, 1924, 1929, etc.
Arrangement
Cataloged. Box 1: A - L; Box 2: M - Z & printed materials.
Subjects
Aikman, Charles Morton.; Alden, W. L. (William Livingston), 1837-1908.; Alexander, William, 1824-1911.; Allen, Grant, 1848-1899.; Atherton, Gertrude Franklin Horn, 1857-1948.; Austin, Alfred, 1835-1913.; Bacheller, Irving, 1859-1950.; Balfour, Arthur James Balfour, Earl of, 1848-1930.; Baring-Gould, S. (Sabine), 1834-1924.; Barlow, Jane, 1857?-1917.; Barr, Robert, 1850-1912.; Becke, Louis, 1855-1913.; Belloc, Hilaire, 1870-1953.; Bentley, George, 1828-1895.; Besant, Walter, Sir, 1836-1901.; Black, William, 1841-1898.; Blackmore, R. D. (Richard Doddridge), 1825-1900.; Bloundelle-Burton, John, 1850-1917.; Boldrewood, Rolf, 1826-1915.; Boothby, Guy Newell, 1867-1905.; Braddon, M. E. (Mary Elizabeth), 1835-1915.; Brenda.; Bullen, Frank Thomas, 1857-1915.; Burgess, Gelett, 1866-1951.; Burnet, John, 1863-1928.; Butler, Samuel, 1835-1902.; Caffyn, Mannington,--Mrs.; Caldecott, William Shaw, 1839-; Cambridge, Ada, 1844-1926.; Capes, Bernard Edward Joseph, d. 1918.; Carr, J. Comyns (Joseph Comyns), 1849-1916.; Castle, Egerton, 1858-1920.; Chambers, Robert W. (Robert William), 1865-1933.; Chesterton, G. K. (Gilbert Keith), 1874-1936.; Clifford, W. K., Mrs., d. 1929.; Collins, Wilkie, 1824-1889.; Conybeare, William James, 1871-; Corelli, Marie, 1855-1924.; Duncan, Sara Jeannette, 1861-1922.; Crawfurd, Oswald, 1834-1909.; Crockett, S. R. (Samuel Rutherford), 1860-1914.; Croker, B. M. (Bithia Mary), d. 1920.; Davidson, John, 1857-1909.; Dougall, L. (Lily), 1858-1923.; Douglas, George Cunninghame Monteath, 1826-1904.; Dowden, Edward, 1843-1913.; Doyle, Arthur Conan, Sir, 1859-1930.; Earle, John, 1824-1903.; Farrar, F. W. (Frederic William), 1831-1903.; Fitzpatrick, Percy, Sir, 1862-1931.; Fowler, Edith Henrietta, 1865-1944.; Fowler, Ellen Thorneycroft, 1860-1929.; Gallon, Tom, 1866-1914.; Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1873-1945.; Gough, Edward John, 1849-; Haddock, John V.; Haggard, H. Rider (Henry Rider), 1856-1925.; Hardy, Thomas, 1840-1928.; Harraden, Beatrice, 1864-1936.; Harte, Bret, 1836-1902.; Hatton, Joseph, 1841-1907.; Herman, Henry, 1832-1894.; Hewlett, Maurice Henry, 1861-1923.; Hill, Headon, 1857-1927.; Hobbes, John Oliver, 1867-1906.; Hodgson, William Earl, d.1910.; Hoey, Frances Cashel, 1830-1908.; Hope, Anthony, 1863-1933.; Hornung, E. W. (Ernest William), 1866-1921.; Hunter, William Wilson, Sir, 1840-1900.; Jerome, Jerome K. (Jerome Klapka), 1859-1927.; Joubert, Carl.; Keats, Gwendoline.; Keith, Leslie (Grace L. Keith Johnston); Kingsley, Rose Georgina, 1845-; Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936.; Lawless, Emily, 1845-1913.; Leland, Charles Godfrey, 1824-1903.; Leng, William C.; Le Queux, William, 1864-1927.; Levett-Yeats, Sidney Kilner.; Lindsay, Lady (Caroline Blanche Elizabeth); Linton, E. Lynn (Elizabeth Lynn), 1822-1898.; Longman, Charles James, 1852-1934.; Lubbock, John, Sir, 1834-1913.; Lytton, Constance, Lady, 1869-1923.; Lytton, Edith Villiers Bulwer-Lytton, Countess of, 1841-; MacCunn, Hamish, 1868-1916.; Maclaren, Ian, 1850-1907.; MacDonald, George, 1824-1905.; Macleod, Donald, 1831-1916.; Madden, Dodgson Hamilton, 1840-; Maitland, Ella Fuller.; Malet, Lucas, 1852-1931.; Mallock, W. H. (William Hurrell), 1849-1923.; Marchmont, Arthur Williams, 1852-1923.; Marlowe, Thomas, 1868-1935.; Marsh, Diana.; Metcalfe, Henry Wray.; Meyer, Charles.; Millais, John Guille, 1865-1931.; Mitford, Bertram, 1855-1914.; Moore, Frank Frankfort, 1855-1931.; Morrison, Arthur, 1863-1945.; Murray, David Christie, 1847-1907.; Newbolt, Henry John, Sir, 1862-1938.; Newnes, George, 1851-1910.; Nicholson, Joseph Shield, 1850-1927.; Norris, W. E. (William Edward), 1847-1925.; Oliphant, Mrs. (Margaret), 1828-1897.; Osbourne, Lloyd, 1868-1947.; Paget, Augustus Berkeley, Sir, 1823-1896.; Parker, Gilbert, 1862-1932.; Payn, James, 1830-1898.; Pearson, Cyril Arthur, Sir, 1866-1921; Phillipps-Woolley, Clive, 1834-; Pollock, Walter Herries, 1850-1926.; Poynter, Edward John, Sir, bart., 1836-1919.; Quiller-Couch, Arthur Thomas, Sir, 1863-1944.; Ralph, Julian, 1853-1903.; Raymond, Walter, 1852-1931.; Roberts, Morley, 1857-1942.; Rowlands, Effie Adelaide, 1866-1936.; Russell, William Clark, 1844-1911.; Sabatier, Paul, 1854-1941.; Sabatini, Rafael, 1875-1950.; Sala, George Augustus, 1828-1895.; Saunders, John, 1811-1895.; Sayce, A. H. (Archibald Henry), 1845-1933.; Scott, Clement, 1841-1904.; Scott, Hugh Stowell, 1862-1903.; Sergeant, Adeline, 1851-1904.; Sidgwick, Cecily Ullmann, d.1934.; Sinclair, May.; Sladen, Douglas Brooke Wheelton, 1856-1947.; Steuart, John A. (John Alexander), 1861-1932.; Stockton, Frank Richard, 1834-1902.; Sutcliffe, Halliwell, 1870-1932.; Swan, Annie S., 1859-1943.; Thomson, H. C. (Harry Craufuird); Thorne, Whyte, 1840-1928.; Townend, Thomas S.; Tytler, Sarah, 1827-1914.; Vachell, Horace Annesley, 1861-1955.; Warden, Florence, 1857-1929.; Watson, Robert A., Mrs., d. 1918.; Watt, Alexander Pollock, d.1914.; Watt, Alexander Strahan, d.1948.; Weaver, Gertrude Renton Colemore Dunn Baillie.; Weyman, Stanley John, 1855-1928.; White, Percy, 1852-1938.; Whiteing, Richard, 1840-1928.; Wilson, Andrew, 1852-1912.; Wingate, F. R. (Francis Reginald), Sir, 1861-1953.; Winter, John Strange, 1856-1911.; Wright, William, 1837-1899.; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939.; Yorke, Curtis.; Authors and publishers--20th century.; English literature--20th century.; Publishers and publishing--20th century.; Accounts.; Galley proofs.; Photographs.; Poems.; Prefaces.; Proofs.; Authors, English.; College teachers.; Critics.; Dramatists, English.; Essayists.; Historians.; Journalists.; Literary agents.; Novelists, English.; Poets, English.; Scholars.; Women authors, English.; Women editors.; Women journalists.; Women novelists, English.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
04/04/94 M-94-04-04 Letters to A.P.Watt 2293B (Rare Book) Purchase
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondents
  - Aikman, Charles Morton (Box 1)
  - Albanesi, Effie Adelaide Maria Henderson, 1866-1936 (Box 1)
  - Alden, William Livingston, 1837-1908 (Box 1)
  - Alexander, William, 1824-1911 (Box 1)
  - Allen, Charles Grant Blairfindie, 1848-1899 (Box 1)
  - Atherton, Gertrude Franklin Horn, 1857-1948 (Box 1)
  - Austin, Alfred, 1835-1913 (Box 1)
  - Avebury, John Lubbock, 1st Baron, 1834-1913 (Box 1)
  - Bacheller, Irving, 1859-1950 (Box 1)
  - Balfour, Arthur James, 1st Earl of Balfour, 1848-1930 (Box 1)
  - Baring-Gould, Sabine, 1834-1924 (Box 1)
  - Barr, Robert, 1850-1912 (Box 1)
  - Bartley, Henry PowellBecke, Louis, 1855-1913 (Box 1)
  - Becke, Louis, 1855-1913 B. (Box 1)
  - Belle (Box 1)
  - Belloc, Hilaire, 1870-1953 (Box 1)
  - Bentley, George, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
  - Bentley, Richard, & Son. (Box 1)
  - Besant, Sir Walter, 1836-1901 (Box 1)
  - Black, A. & C, (Publishers) Limited (Box 1)
  - Black, William, 1841-1898 (Box 1)
  - Blackmore, Richard Doddridge, 1825-1900 (Box 1)
  - Bloundelle-Burton, John, 1850-1917 (Box 1)
  - Boothby, Guy Newell, 1867-1905 (Box 1)
  - Braddon, Mary Elizabeth, 1837-1915 (Box 1)
  - Brenda (pseud.) (Box 1)
  - Browne, Thomas Alexander, 1826-1915 (Box 1)
  - Bullen, Frank Thomas, 1857-1915 (Box 1)
  - Burgess, Gelett, 1866-1951 (Box 1)
  - Burnet, John, 1863-1928 (Box 1)
  - Butler, Samuel, 1835-1902 (Box 1)
  - Caffyn, Kathleen Mannington Hunt, d.1926 (Box 1)
  - Caldecott, William Shaw, b.1839 (Box 1)
  - Cambridge, Ada, 1844-1926 (Box 1)
  - Capes, Bernard Edward Joseph, d.1918 (Box 1)
  - Carr, Joseph William Comyns, 1849-1916 (Box 1)
  - Castle, Egerton, 1858-1920 (Box 1)
  - Chambers, Robert William, 1865-1933 (Box 1)
  - Chatto & Windus (Box 1)
  - Chesterton, Gilbert Keith, 1874-1936 (Box 1)
  - Clacy, George H. (Box 1)
  - Clifford, Lucy Lane (Mrs William K.), d.1929 (Box 1)
  - Conybeare, William James, b.1871 (Box 1)
  - Corelli, Marie, 1855-1924 (Box 1)
  - Cotes, Sara Jeanette Duncan, 1862-1922 (Box 1)
  - Craigie, Pearl Mary Teresa, 1867-1906 (Box 1)
  - Crawfurd, Oswald John Frederick, 1834-1909 (Box 1)
  - Crockett, Samuel Rutherford, 1860-1914 (Box 1)
  - Croker, Bithia Mary Sheppard, d.1920 (Box 1)
  - Davidson, John, 1857-1909 (Box 1)
  - Doig, William (Box 1)
  - Dougall, Lily, 1858-1923 (Box 1)
  - Douglas, George Cunninghame Monteath, 1826-1904 (Box 1)
  - Dowden, Edward, 1843-1913 (Box 1)
  - Doyle, Sir Arthur Conan (Box 1)
  - Earle, John, 1824-1903 (Box 1)
  - Farrar, Frederic William, 1831-1903 (Box 1)
  - Felkin, Ellen Thorneycroft Fowler, 1860-1929 (Box 1)
  - Fitzpatrick, Sir James Percy, 1862-1931 (Box 1)
  - Fowler, Edith Henrietta, b.1865 (Box 1)
  - Gallon, Tom, 1866-1914 (Box 1)
  - Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1874-1945 (Box 1)
  - Gough, Edward John, b.1849 (Box 1)
  - Graham, John (per George Horace Lorimer, 1868-1937) (Box 1)
  - Grainger, Francis Edward, 1857-1927 (Box 1)
  - Grant, Christian M. Browne (Mrs James) (Box 1)
  - Haddock, John V. (Box 1)
  - Haggard, Sir Henry Rider, 1856-1925 (Box 1)
  - Hanson, C. (Box 1)
  - Hardy, Thomas (Box 1)
  - Harraden, Beatrice, 1864-1936 (Box 1)
  - Harrison, Mary St.Leger Kingsley, 1852-1931 (Box 1)
  - Harte, Bret, 1836-1902 (Box 1)
  - Hatton, Joseph, 1841-1907 (Box 1)
  - Hawkins, Sir Anthony Hope, 1863-1933 (Box 1)
  - Herman, Henry, 1832-1894 (Box 1)
  - Hewlett, Maurice Henry, 1861-1923 (Box 1)
  - Hodgson, William Earl, d.1910 (Box 1)
  - Hoey, Frances Sarah Johnston Cashel, 1830-1908 (Box 1)
  - Hornung, Ernest William, 1866-1921 (Box 1)
  - Hunter, Sir William Wilson, 1840-1900 (Box 1)
  - Hurst & Blackett Limited (Box 1)
  - James, Florence Alice Price, 1857-1929 (Box 1)
  - Jerome, Jerome Klapka, 1859-1927 (Box 1)
  - Johnston, Grace Leslie Keith (Box 1)
  - Joubert, Carl (Box 1)
  - Keats, Gwendoline (Box 1)
  - Keddie, Henrietta, 1827-1914 (Box 1)
  - Kegan Paul, Trench & Co., Publishers (Box 1)
  - Kingsley, Rose Georgina, b.1845 (Box 1)
  - Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936 (Box 1)
  - Lawless, Emily, 1845-1913 (Box 1)
  - Leland, Charles Godfrey, 1824-1903 (Box 1)
  - Leng, William C. (Box 1)
  - Le Queux, William Tufnell, 1864-1927 (Box 1)
  - Levett-Yeats, Sidney Kilner (Box 1)
  - Lindsay, Caroline Blanche Elizabeth Fitzroy, Lady, 1844-1912 (Box 1)
  - Linton, Eliza Lynn, 1822-1898 (Box 1)
  - Longman, Charles James, 1852-1934 (Box 1)
  - Longmans, Green & Co. (Box 1)
  - Lytton, Lady Constance Georgina Bulwer-, b.1869 (Box 1)
  - Lytton, Edith Villiers Bulwer-Lytton, Countess of, b.1841 (Box 1)
  - MacCunn, Hamish, 1868-1916 (Box 2)
  - MacDonald, George, 1824-1905 (Box 2)
  - Macleod, Donald, 1831-1916 (Box 2)
  - Madden, Dodgson Hamilton, b.1840 (Box 2)
  - Maitland, Ella Fuller (Box 2)
  - Mallock, William Hurrell, 1849-1923 (Box 2)
  - Marchmont, Arthur Williams, 1852-1923 (Box 2)
  - Marlowe, Thomas, 1868-1935 (Box 2)
  - Marsh, Diana (pseud.) (Box 2)
  - Metcalfe, Henry Wray (Box 2)
  - Methuen & Co., Publishers (Box 2)
  - Meyer, Charles (Box 2)
  - Millais, John Guille, 1865-1931 (Box 2)
  - Mitford, Bertram, 1855-1914 (Box 2)
  - Moore, Frank Frankfort, 1855-1931 (Box 2)
  - Morrison, Arthur, 1863-1945 (Box 2)
  - Murray, David Christie, 1847-1907 (Box 2)
  - Newbolt, Sir Henry John, 1862-1938 (Box 2)
  - Newnes, Sir George, 1851-1910 (Box 2)
  - Nicholson, Joseph Shield, 1850-1927 (Box 2)
  - Norris, William Edward, 1847-1925 (Box 2)
  - Oliphant, Margaret Oliphant Wilson, 1828-1897 (Box 2)
  - Osbourne, Lloyd, 1868-1947 (Box 2)
  - Paget, Sir Augustus Berkeley, 1823-1896 (Box 2)
  - Parker, Sir Gilbert, 1862-1932 (Box 2)
  - Payn, James, 1830-1898 (Box 2)
  - Pearson, Sir Cyril Arthur, 1866-1921 (Box 2)
  - Phillipps-Woolley, Clive, b.1854 (Box 2)
  - Pollock, Walter Herries, 1850-1926 (Box 2)
  - Poynter, Sir Edward John, 1836-1919 (Box 2)
  - Quiller-Couch, Sir Arthur Thomas, 1863-1944 (Box 2)
  - Ralph, Julian, 1853-1903 (Box 2)
  - Raymond, Walter, 1852-1931 (Box 2)
  - Richmond Lee, Susan Long (Mrs John W.) (Box 2)
  - Roberts, Morley, 1857-1942 (Box 2)
  - Russell, William Clark, 1844-1911 (Box 2)
  - Sabatier, Paul, 1854-1941 (Box 2)
  - Sabatini, Rafael, 1875-1950 (Box 2)
  - Sala, George Augustus Henry, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
  - Saunders, John, 1810-1895 (Box 2)
  - Scott, Clement William, 1841-1904 (Box 2)
  - Scott, Hugh Stowell, 1862-1903 (Box 2)
  - Sergeant, Adeline, 1851-1904 (Box 2)
  - Sidgwick, Cecily Ullmann, d.1934 (Box 2)
  - Sinclair, May, ca.1865-1946 (Box 2)
  - 2 Sladen, Douglas Brooke Wheelton, 1856-1947 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Catherine Grant Furley (Box 2)
  - Smith, William Francis, 1842-1919 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Elder & Co. (Box 2)
  - Stannard, Henrietta Eliza Vaughan Palmer, 1856-1911 (Box 2)
  - Steuart, John Alexander, 1861-1932 (Box 2)
  - Stockton, Frank Richard, 1834-1902 (Box 2)
  - Sutcliffe, Halliwell, 1870-1932 (Box 2)
  - Swan, Annie S. (Mrs James Burdett-Smith), 1859-1943 (Box 2)
  - Thomson, Harry Craufuird (Box 2)
  - Townend, Thomas S. (Box 2)
  - Vachell, Horace Annesley, 1861-1955 (Box 2)
  - Watson, Elizabeth Sophia Fletcher (Mrs Robert A.), d.1918 (Box 2)
  - Watson, John, 1850-1907 (Box 2)
  - Watt, Alexander Strahan, d.1948 (Box 2)
  - Weaver, Gertrude Renton Colemore Dunn Baillie (Mrs Harold B.) (Box 2)
  - Weyman, Stanley John, 1855-1928 (Box 2)
  - White, Percy, 1852-1938 (Box 2)
  - Whiteing, Richard, 1840-1928 (Box 2)
  - Wilson, Andrew, 1852-1912 (Box 2)
  - Wingate, Sir Francis Reginald, 1861-1953 (Box 2)
  - Wright, William, 1837-1899 (Box 2)
  - Yeats, William Butler, 1865-1939 (Box 2)
- Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
  - Leland, Charled Godfrey, 1824-1903 (Box 2)
  - Sayce, Archibald Henry, 1845-1933 (Box 2)
  - Watt, A.P., & Son (Box 2)